<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo revision="0.1.1">
    <title>BKChem</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Beda</firstname>
      <surname>Kosata</surname>
    </author>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>Beda Kosata</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Copyright (c) 2002,2004  Beda Kosata.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, no Back-Cover Texts.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Foreword and Warning</title>
    <para>I am not a programmer by training. Programming is just my hobby and I am doing it for fun.
    Therefor you should not expect BKChem to be perfect or even usable. The coding style is probably horrible and trying 
    to read the code may seriously affect your mental health :)</para>
    <para>You are however welcome to read the code, modify it and send me suggestions or patches. I'm still learning. On the other
    hand don't flame me about the style - you have been warned.</para>
    <para>Any reports on bugs are also welcome (especially those with suggestions on their sources or
    solutions).</para>
    <para>Before you start to use BKChem, you should read the license. BKChem is distributed under
    GNU GPL (see the file gpl.txt in the main distribution directory). This license gives you
    freedom to study and modify BKChem as you wish. On the other hand you should be warned that
    <emphasis> "This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
    WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
    PURPOSE"</emphasis></para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>Users Guide</title>
    <chapter>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>BKChem is a chemical drawing program written in Python. The documentation as well as the
	program itself are in constant development. Therefor this manual is not meant to be
	complete, but rather tries to cover the very basics and the things that are not easy to find
	out without help. On the other hand many things are so self-evident that it would be useless
	to describe them. If you find that something you would like to know is not described in this
	manual, please email me to <email>beda@zirael.org</email>.</para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
      <title>Drawing</title>
      <sect1>
	<title>Introduction to the terms</title>
	<para>Before we begin I should explain some terms that are used in the documentation and in
	the program itself.
        <table frame="all">
	    <title>Used terms</title>
	    <tgroup cols="2">
	      <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="60pt"/>
	      <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="360pt"/>
	      <thead>
		<row>
		  <entry>Term</entry>
		  <entry>Definition</entry>
		</row>
	      </thead>
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>item</entry>
		  <entry>Any single undividable piece of the drawing - atom, bond, arrow point,
		  plus. Not a molecule or arrow (see container).</entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry>container</entry>
		  <entry>Containers serve as a storage place for items (e.g. molecule stores atoms
		  and bonds). Further I will use the term container also for texts and pluses even
		  if they are also items (If it does not make sense to you don't just ignore it). As
		  a synonym for container I will also use object or top-level object.</entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry>focus(ed)</entry>
		  <entry>Focused items are those that have a mouse pointer over them. The focus is
		  usually visualized by some change of the item (e.g. circle drawn around atom, grey
		  background of text etc.)</entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry>select(ed)</entry>
		  <entry>In contrast to focus, to select an item the user must take some action
		  (usually click the mouse while the pointer is over an item (it is focused). The
		  focus follows the mouse pointer, the selection is permanent until some action that
		  unselects the item is performed. In contrast with focus it is possible to have more
		  selected items.</entry>
		</row>

		<row>
		  <entry>mode</entry>
		  <entry>BKChem has several modes for different operations (e.g. for drawing
		  molecules, drawing arrow, text, rotating existing objects). You select the mode by
		  selecting one of the buttons on the top of the application window. You can find more on
		  individual modes in the following chapters.</entry>
		</row>

	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table></para>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
	<title>Simple drawing</title>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Bond-by-bond drawing</title>
	  <para>The bond-by-bond drawing in BKChem is performed in the "draw mode".</para>
	  <para>The drawing is realized in a very intuitive way. You can just click on the
	    drawing canvas and two atoms with a single bond between them will appear. By default the
	    atoms are carbons and their symbol is not drawn. When you change the atom symbol to
	    something else the symbol will appear. To attach more atoms to the currently drawn two, just
	    focus one of them and click a mouse. By default the new atoms are added so that the new bond
	    has angle of 120 deg. If you want to change that you can instead of a click on focused atom use
	    dragging. Press down a mouse button on a focused atom and without releasing it move the
	    mouse. You will find out that the new bond is drawn in a direction of your mouse move and
	    keeps moving while you keep dragging. To help you with precision of the drawing, there are
	    several possible resolutions of the angle produced by dragging. The default is 30deg and is
	    suitable for usual drawing (perfect for 6 membered rings). The resolution of 18deg is great
	    for five membered rings and the others (6 and 1) are for finer work. For completely
	    freestyle drawing use the "freestyle" submode.</para>
	  <para>To create double or triple bonds, just click on a bond in a "draw mode" and the bond
	    order will increase by 1. After triple bond it will fall back to simple bond. This way you
	    can also change the centering of the double bond (whether the two lines that form double
	    bond will be centered and when not on which side the second line will appear). If you only
	    want to change the centering of double bond you can just click it while holding "Shift"
	    key.</para>
	  <para>By changing the bond type of drawn bonds you can create stereo-bonds.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Templates</title>
	  <para>BKChem comes with set of ready-to-use templates of common rings. To use them just
	    select the "template mode" and then select a template.</para>
	  <para>The behavior of template depends on where you place it. Clicking on the canvas
	    just creates the molecule from the template. Clicking on atoms or bonds attaches the
	    template to the existing molecule in different ways (depending on whether you clicked bond
	    or atom and whether the atom had one or more other bonds) - just try it to see.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Arrows</title>
	  <para>For drawing of arrows use "arrow mode". The way to draw arrow resembles bond-by-bond
	    drawing of molecules. The arrow can be extended from both sides points can be even inserted
	    inside the arrow. To draw arrows in different than horizontal position used the dragging
	    while drawing.</para>
	  <para>You can select on which side the arrow-head will be drawn by clicking the arrow (the
	    line, not the point) in the arrow mode. The arrow-head position will cycle in the
	    start-end-both-none cycle (so you can use the arrow also for drawing lines).</para>
	  <para>To change the appearance of existing arrow you can move individual points (after you
	  select them - see the following parts of this chapter.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Text</title>
	  <para>Most of this section applies not only to texts but also to atoms that have visible
	    text. To create or modify the text use the "text mode". The text can be set in any
	    mode (there is a difference between setting and modifying text - when modifying text you
	    can just change it, when setting it you have to retype the whole sequence).</para>
	  <sect3>
	    <title>Text formatting</title>
	    <para>To give the user a simple way to alter the font properties of text (italic, bold,
	      subscript and superscript) the text is entered as an XML fragment. You do not specify
	      the enclosing tag (this is done automatically by the program), just the formating. For
	      instance the text "hi, &lt;i>are you ready
	      to &lt;b>rock&lt;/b>&lt;/i>?" will display "are you ready to" as italic and "rock" as
	      bold-italic. For subscript and superscript use &lt;sub> and &lt;sup> respectively.</para>
	    <para>When using XML formating there is a problem with using characters as &lt; and &amp;
	      because they are treated as special in XML. When you enter some text such as "a&lt;b"
	      that cannot be parsed as XML, the program will automatically "escape" all the special
	      characters, thus giving you the right result. When you need only some of the special
	      characters to be escaped (e.g. for &lt;i>a&lt;b&lt;/i>" you want to escape the &lt; only
	      in the "a&lt;b") you must do it manually. This means entering an "escape sequence" instead
	      of the special character. For "&lt;" use "&amp;lt;" and for "&amp;" use "&amp;amp;" (and
	      "&amp;amp;amp;" for "&amp;amp;" :). Easy, isn't it?</para>
	  </sect3>
	  <sect3>
	    <title>Setting and modifying text</title>
	    <para>When you hit a "Space" button with some atoms or texts selected or when you click
	    an atom or text in "text mode" or click the canvas in "text mode", the "edit pool" will
	    be activated letting you enter your text. To apply the entered text hit "Enter" or press
	    one of the buttons on side of "edit pool". To cancel the action hit "Escape". The three
	    buttons are used for setting text in different modes. The "Set" button serves for
	    applying the text just as it was entered, "Set &amp; Interpret" will search the inner
	    database of BKChem to find if the entered text has some known interpretation. The
	    "Sub-numbers" is used to turn all numbers in subscript and is useful for molecular
	    formulas that are not known to BKChem.</para>
	  </sect3>
	</sect2>
      </sect1>
      <sect1>
	<title>Modifying the drawing</title>
	<para>To manipulate the items use the "edit mode". This mode is used for moving items or
	  containers, selecting items etc.</para>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Selection</title>
	  <para>To select an item just click it in the "edit mode". By default selecting an item
	    unselects all previously selected items. To change this, hold the "Shift" key while
	    clicking the items.</para>
	  <para>By dragging a mouse with <keycode>button-1</keycode> down and nothing focused you
	    can select all items in a rectangle. The "Shift" key works in the same way as in
	    individual selections.</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Moving objects or items</title>
	  <para>There are two different ways of moving objects or items. The first is used for
	    moving of arbitrary number of items. Just select them and then catch one of them with
	    mouse and drag them.</para>
	  <para>For moving of one object (container - molecule) (which is very usual situation)
	    you don't need to select it. Just catch some <emphasis>unselected</emphasis> item from
	    this object and drag it.
	    (Note: You can see that behavior of dragging items with mouse depends on whether the
	    item was or wasn't selected.) (Tip: The moving of a molecule in this way performs much better, so use it. When
	    moving a huge number of individually selected items the dragging can be horribly
	    slow.)
	  </para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Deleting items</title>
	  <para>You can delete selected items in any mode by simply pressing "Delete" key. Atoms
	    are deleted with their bonds and all orphan atoms (atoms with no bonds) are also
	    deleted. When necessary the molecule is after deletion of some atoms split to two or more
	    separate molecules.<tip>
	      <para>Newly created atoms or other items are automatically selected. Thus if you want
		to delete atom just drawn, simply press the "Delete" key.</para>
	    </tip>
	  </para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Aligning</title>
	  <para>To align containers, select them and then use either the "align menu" or
	    key-binding (C-a 'x'; where 'x' is one of 'tblrhv' - 't' stands for 'top', 'b' for
	    'bottom', 'l' for 'left', 'r' for 'right', 'v' for 'vertical center' and 'h' for
	      'horizontal center'). E.g. - "C-a b" moves all selected container (containers with at
	    least one item selected) down so that their bottoms are in line.</para>
	</sect2>
	  <sect2>
	  <title>Modifying item properties</title>
	  <para>You can change various properties of selected items by right-clicking any of
	    them. A dialog window will appear that will let you do that.</para>
	  </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1>
	<title>Key bindings</title>
	<para>In the menu there are accelerator keys displayed on the right side of some of the
	commands. You can use these key sequences as shorcuts to trigger the respective actions
	without having to go to the menu.</para>
	<para>The style of key bindings is very similar to that of Emacs. So if you are familiar
	with this concept (you know what "C-x C-f" means and how does it differ from "C-x f") you
	can skip this chapter. If you know nothing about "C-x C-f" then here is	a short intro.</para>
	<para>Each key-sequence can be composed from any number of individual keystrokes. Each keystroke
	than consists of optional modifier(s) and a key. The modifiers are "C" for "Control", "M"
	for "Meta", "A" for "Alt" and "S" for "Shift". For example
	"C-x C-f" is composed of two keystrokes. The first part tells you that you should press "x"
	while holding "Control" ("C"). Then, to finish the sequence, you have press "f" together
	with "Control" again. On contrary the sequence "C-x f" has the same first keystroke but
	before you press the "f" you must release the "Control" (otherwise you will end up with "C-x
	C-f"). It is also possible to have more modifiers in one keystroke - e.g. "C-M-S-k" means
	that you have to press "k" while holding simultaneously "Control", "Meta" and "Shift"
	keys. The best way to get used to this concept is by practice. So try it inside of BKChem
	or get Emacs.</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Saving files</title>
      <sect1>
	<title>Native formats</title>
	<para>Native format of BKChem is based on XML and is called CDML (chemical drawing markup
	  language). This format is, on contrary to CML (chemical markup language) which is designed
	  to describe the chemistry from the semantic point of view, designed to describe the
	  chemical drawing from the perspective of representation.</para>
	<para>CDML is however just internal format of BKChem and does not have any broad
	  acceptance. To use the graphical output of BKChem it was necessary to export the data into
	  some standard graphical format, preferentially SVG. This approach has however disadvantage
	  that it forces users to maintain two versions of each document, one with data for BKChem
	  and one with their graphical representation. Fortunately it is possible to embed foreign
	  data into SVG and because SVG is ideal format for vector graphics I have
	  embedded CDML into it. This way we have format (available from version 0.1.1) that
	  can be immediately viewed in 
	  SVG enabled programs and still has the data necessary for right interpretation by
	  BKChem. To distinguish this new format from normal SVG I use the term CD-SVG.</para>
	<para>This means that you can store the drawings you create in BKChem in two formats - CDML
	  and CD-SVG. Both these formats are also available in their gzipped form (compression by
	  gzip is almost standard way to make XML files smaller) which needs usually only 10-25% of
	  the space needed by the unzipped form. Preferred file format is CD-SVG or if you need
	  smaller file size its gzipped form. If you don't need the SVG representation you can also
	  use the pure CDML. (Export to pure SVG is also available).</para>
      </sect1>
      <sect1>
	<title>Export formats</title>
	<para>In time of writing of this paragraph BKChem supports export only to SVG (see the
	  section above for more information on BKChem and SVG). There are other exports available
	  which are only experimental and incomplete. These are PNG (cannot export text), PostScript
	  (problems with right postscript font selection) and PovRay (just a funny export not
	  intended for something serious (the rendered scenes can however be very nice)) - see
	  http://www.povray.org for more information about PovRay.</para>
      </sect1>
    </chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Modes</title>
  <para>Central part of the functionality of BKChem is provided by the so called modes. There is
  always one active mode, which determines how the objects respond to user actions. You can choose
  the mode on the <xref linkend="pict.modes-all"/>.</para>

  <figure id="pict.modes-all">
    <title>Mode selection panel</title>
    <screenshot>
      <graphic fileref="img/modes-all.png"/>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

<!--  <segmentedlist>
    <segtitle>Edit mode</segtitle>
    <seglistitem>
      <seg></seg>
    </seglistitem>
  </segmentedlist>
-->
</chapter>
</part>

<part>
    <title>Programmers Guide</title>
    <chapter>
      <title>Intro</title>
      <para>Well, sure there will be some info on BKChem structure somewhere in the future. But
      for now I am too busy with other more interesting and important things.</para>
    </chapter>
  </part>








  <appendix id="gfdl">
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
    <!-- - GNU Project - Free Software Foundation (FSF) -->
    <!-- LINK REV="made" HREF="mailto:webmasters@gnu.org" -->
    

    <!-- sect1>
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title -->
    
    <para>Version 1.1, March 2000</para>

<blockquote>
<para>Copyright (C) 2000  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
</blockquote>

<sect1 label="0">
<title>PREAMBLE</title>

<para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook,
    or other written document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
    assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
    with or without modifying it, either commercially or
    noncommercially.  Secondarily, this License preserves for the
    author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not
    being considered responsible for modifications made by
    others.</para>

<para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
    derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the
    same sense.  It complements the GNU General Public License, which
    is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

<para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
    for free software, because free software needs free documentation:
    a free program should come with manuals providing the same
    freedoms that the software does.  But this License is not limited
    to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
    regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
    printed book.  We recommend this License principally for works
    whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="1">
<title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

<para>This License applies to any manual or other work that
    contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
    distributed under the terms of this License.  The "Document",
    below, refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the
    public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you".</para>

<para>A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work
    containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
    verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
    language.</para>

<para>A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter
    section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
    relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
    Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains
    nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject.
    (For example, if the Document is in part a textbook of
    mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)
    The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with
    the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
    philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
    them.</para>

<para>The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections
    whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections,
    in the notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

<para>The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that
    are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
    notice that says that the Document is released under this
    License.</para>

<para>A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
    machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification
    is available to the general public, whose contents can be viewed
    and edited directly and straightforwardly with generic text
    editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs
    or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
    is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
    translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
    formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
    whose markup has been designed to thwart or discourage subsequent
    modification by readers is not Transparent.  A copy that is not
    "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

<para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
    plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
    format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
    standard-conforming simple HTML designed for human modification.
    Opaque formats include PostScript, PDF, proprietary formats that
    can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML
    or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
    available, and the machine-generated HTML produced by some word
    processors for output purposes only.</para>

<para>The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page
    itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly,
    the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
    For works in formats which do not have any title page as such,
    "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of
    the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
    text.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="2">
<title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

<para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium,
    either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this
    License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this
    License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and
    that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
    License.  You may not use technical measures to obstruct or
    control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
    distribute.  However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
    copies.  If you distribute a large enough number of copies you
    must also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

<para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
    above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="3">
<title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

<para>If you publish printed copies of the Document numbering more
    than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts,
    you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and
    legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front
    cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover.  Both covers must
    also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these
    copies.  The front cover must present the full title with all
    words of the title equally prominent and visible.  You may add
    other material on the covers in addition.  Copying with changes
    limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the
    Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim
    copying in other respects.</para>

<para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
    fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
    reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
    adjacent pages.</para>

<para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
    numbering more than 100, you must either include a
    machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or
    state in or with each Opaque copy a publicly-accessible
    computer-network location containing a complete Transparent copy
    of the Document, free of added material, which the general
    network-using public has access to download anonymously at no
    charge using public-standard network protocols.  If you use the
    latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you
    begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that
    this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
    location until at least one year after the last time you
    distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or
    retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

<para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the
    authors of the Document well before redistributing any large
    number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an
    updated version of the Document.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="4">
<title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

<para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the
    Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided
    that you release the Modified Version under precisely this
    License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the
    Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
    Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it.  In addition,
    you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

<orderedlist numeration="upperalpha">
<listitem><para>Use in the Title Page
      (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the
      Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
      there were any, be listed in the History section of the
      Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version if
      the original publisher of that version gives permission.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>List on the Title Page,
      as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for
      authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
      together with at least five of the principal authors of the
      Document (all of its principal authors, if it has less than
      five).</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>State on the Title page
      the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the
      publisher.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve all the
      copyright notices of the Document.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Add an appropriate
      copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other
      copyright notices.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Include, immediately
      after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public
      permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
      License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve in that license
      notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover
      Texts given in the Document's license notice.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Include an unaltered
      copy of this License.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve the section
      entitled "History", and its title, and add to it an item stating
      at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
      Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If there is no
      section entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating
      the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given
      on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
      Version as stated in the previous sentence.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve the network
      location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a
      Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
      locations given in the Document for previous versions it was
      based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.  You
      may omit a network location for a work that was published at
      least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
      publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>In any section entitled
      "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", preserve the section's
      title, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of
      each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications
      given therein.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Preserve all the
      Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and
      in their titles.  Section numbers or the equivalent are not
      considered part of the section titles.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Delete any section
      entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section may not be included in
      the Modified Version.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>Do not retitle any
      existing section as "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with
      any Invariant Section.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections
    or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no
    material copied from the Document, you may at your option
    designate some or all of these sections as invariant.  To do this,
    add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified
    Version's license notice.  These titles must be distinct from any
    other section titles.</para>

<para>You may add a section entitled "Endorsements", provided it
    contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by
    various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that
    the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
    definition of a standard.</para>

<para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
    Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
    end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one
    passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be
    added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the
    Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
    previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity
    you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
    replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
    publisher that added the old one.</para>

<para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by
    this License give permission to use their names for publicity for
    or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="5">
<title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

<para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
    under this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for
    modified versions, provided that you include in the combination
    all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents,
    unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
    combined work in its license notice.</para>

<para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this
    License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced
    with a single copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with
    the same name but different contents, make the title of each such
    section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the
    name of the original author or publisher of that section if known,
    or else a unique number.  Make the same adjustment to the section
    titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
    the combined work.</para>

<para>In the combination, you must combine any sections entitled
    "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
    entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections entitled
    "Acknowledgements", and any sections entitled "Dedications".  You
    must delete all sections entitled "Endorsements."</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="6">
<title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

<para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and
    other documents released under this License, and replace the
    individual copies of this License in the various documents with a
    single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you
    follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of
    the documents in all other respects.</para>

<para>You may extract a single document from such a collection,
    and distribute it individually under this License, provided you
    insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
    follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
    copying of that document.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="7">
<title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>
<para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
    separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of
    a storage or distribution medium, does not as a whole count as a
    Modified Version of the Document, provided no compilation
    copyright is claimed for the compilation.  Such a compilation is
    called an "aggregate", and this License does not apply to the
    other self-contained works thus compiled with the Document, on
    account of their being thus compiled, if they are not themselves
    derivative works of the Document.</para>

<para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
    these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than
    one quarter of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts
    may be placed on covers that surround only the Document within the
    aggregate.  Otherwise they must appear on covers around the whole
    aggregate.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="8">
<title>TRANSLATION</title>

<para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
    distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section
    4.  Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires
    special permission from their copyright holders, but you may
    include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition
    to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may
    include a translation of this License provided that you also
    include the original English version of this License.  In case of
    a disagreement between the translation and the original English
    version of this License, the original English version will
    prevail.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="9">
<title>TERMINATION</title>
<para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
    Document except as expressly provided for under this License.  Any
    other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the
    Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
    under this License.  However, parties who have received copies, or
    rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
    terminated so long as such parties remain in full
    compliance.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="10">
<title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

<para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised
    versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.
    Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
    version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
    concerns.  See <ulink
    url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/">http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/</ulink>.</para>

<para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing
    version number.  If the Document specifies that a particular
    numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to
    it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
    either of that specified version or of any later version that has
    been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
    If the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
    you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
    Free Software Foundation.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 label="">
<title>How to use this License for your documents</title>

<para>To use this License in a document you have written, include
    a copy of the License in the document and put the following
    copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>

<blockquote><para>
Copyright (c)  YEAR  YOUR NAME.
      Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
      under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1
      or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
      with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
      Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.
      A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
      Free Documentation License".
</para></blockquote>

<para>If you have no Invariant Sections, write "with no Invariant
    Sections" instead of saying which ones are invariant.  If you have
    no Front-Cover Texts, write "no Front-Cover Texts" instead of
    "Front-Cover Texts being LIST"; likewise for Back-Cover
    Texts.</para>

<para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program
    code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
    choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public
    License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
</sect1>

</appendix>
</book>
      
